<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doi_batch xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/schema/5.3.1"
           xmlns:fr="http://www.crossref.org/fundref.xsd"
           xmlns:jats="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/JATS1"
           xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
           xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
           xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.crossref.org/schema/5.3.1 https://www.crossref.org/schemas/crossref5.3.1.xsd"
           version="5.3.1">
   <head>
      <doi_batch_id>gbpublisher-01-EDITORIAL-V01-N01-20260629034038</doi_batch_id>
      <timestamp>20260629034038</timestamp>
      <depositor>
         <depositor_name>Editorial Universidad de San Telmo</depositor_name>
         <email_address>hola@adl.org</email_address>
      </depositor>
      <registrant>Universidad de San Telmo</registrant>
   </head>
   <body>
      <journal>
         <journal_metadata language="es" reference_distribution_opts="any">
            <full_title>Agenda Digital Latinoamericana</full_title>
            <abbrev_title>Agend. digit. Latinoam.</abbrev_title>
            <issn media_type="electronic">1853-0028</issn>
         </journal_metadata>
         <journal_issue>
            <publication_date media_type="online">
               <month>06</month>
               <day>26</day>
               <year>2026</year>
            </publication_date>
            <journal_volume>
               <volume>01</volume>
            </journal_volume>
            <issue>01</issue>
         </journal_issue>
         <journal_article language="es"
                          publication_type="full_text"
                          reference_distribution_opts="any">
            <titles>
               <title>Las deudas pendientes de la digitalización en América Latina</title>
               <original_language_title language="en">The Pending Challenges of Digitalization in Latin America</original_language_title>
            </titles>
            <contributors>
               <person_name sequence="first" contributor_role="author">
                  <given_name>Andrea Esther</given_name>
                  <surname>Liberatore</surname>
                  <ORCID authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0009-0003-9648-5013</ORCID>
               </person_name>
            </contributors>
            <jats:abstract>
               <jats:p xml:lang="es">Este artículo editorial examina el impacto de la pandemia de COVID-19 como acelerador de la transformación tecnológica en América Latina, analizando cómo la migración virtual profundizó las asimetrías socioeconómicas preexistentes. El texto presenta un diagnóstico dicotómico: reconoce la expansión de la conectividad pospandemia, pero denuncia la persistencia de una "brecha digital de segundo nivel", caracterizada por limitaciones de acceso material y falta de competencias digitales en sectores vulnerables. Se postula que la digitalización sin políticas públicas integrales actúa como un vector que reproduce desigualdades históricas de género, etnia y territorio. Finalmente, se introduce este número de la revista, cuyas contribuciones abordan la problemática bajo la premisa de que la transformación digital no debe aislarse de sus condiciones materiales.</jats:p>
            </jats:abstract>
            <jats:abstract>
               <jats:p xml:lang="en">This editorial examines the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic as an accelerator of technological transformation in Latin America, analyzing how virtual migration deepened pre-existing socioeconomic asymmetries. The text presents a dichotomous diagnosis: it recognizes post-pandemic connectivity expansion while denouncing the persistence of a "second-level digital divide," characterized by material access limitations and a lack of digital skills in vulnerable sectors. It argues that digitalization without comprehensive, intersectional public policies acts as a vector that reproduces historical inequalities of gender, ethnicity, and territory. Finally, this journal issue is introduced, featuring contributions that address the issue under the premise that digital transformation cannot be isolated from its material conditions.</jats:p>
            </jats:abstract>
            <publication_date media_type="online">
               <month>06</month>
               <day>26</day>
               <year>2026</year>
            </publication_date>
            <pages>
               <first_page>1</first_page>
               <last_page>7</last_page>
            </pages>
            <program xmlns="http://www.crossref.org/AccessIndicators.xsd">
               <free_to_read/>
               <license_ref applies_to="vor">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</license_ref>
            </program>
            <doi_data>
               <doi>10.1787/7a127615-es</doi>
               <resource content_version="vor" mime_type="text/html">https://www.clacso.org/ciencia-tecnologia-y-sociedad-en-america-latina/</resource>
            </doi_data>
            <citation_list>
               <citation key="bib-2566-CEPAL2021">
                  <unstructured_citation>CEPAL (
      2021
     ). Tecnologías digitales para un nuevo futuro. CEPAL.</unstructured_citation>
               </citation>
            </citation_list>
         </journal_article>
      </journal>
   </body>
</doi_batch>
